Gould, Samuel; Papers apap058
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Samuel B. Gould Papers
1933-1997
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Gould, Samuel B.
apap058
4.34 cubic ft.
The Samuel B. Gould Papers document his personal life as well as his many professional positions in education, including his tenure as chancellor of the State University of New York.
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Acquisition Information
Samuel B. Gould donated his papers in 1988 to the M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives. When Dr. Gould passed away in 1997, his children gave some of his personal materials to Dr. Martin Fausold who was researching both the history of the State University of New York and Dr. Gould. Fausold later donated these materials along with his own papers in 2008.
Biographical Sketch
Samuel Brookner Gould was an American educator known for promoting expanded access to education through the use of non-traditional means, such as educational television, college teacher-mentor systems, and universities without walls. Among his most important positions were the presidency of the Educational Broadcasting System (1962-64); the Chancellorship of the State University of New York (1964-70); and the chairman of the Carnegie Commission on Non-Traditional Study (1971-74).
Samuel Gould was born in Shelton, Connecticut, on October 11, 1910. At the age of 16 he attended Bates College in Maine, where he was a general assistant to the president. He graduated in 1930. He attended Oxford University briefly in 1931 but left due to financial difficulties. Gould worked for New England Telephone and Telegraph until he accepted a teaching position in English at William Hall High School in West Hartford, Connecticut (1932-38). He also worked part time for a radio station. In 1936, he married Laura Johanna Ohmen, a native of Finland. From 1938 to 1947, Gould headed the department of speech at Brookline High School in Massachusetts while working on his Ph.D. from Harvard. He had previously completed his M.A. at New York University.
Gould's doctoral work was interrupted by World War II. He served in the Navy as a Lt. Commander, PTD, gaining honors. After the war, he helped establish Boston University's Communications Department and served as an assistant to the president from 1951 to 1953. In 1954, Gould became president of Antioch College in Ohio, a position he held until he was appointed chancellor of the University of California at Santa Barbara in 1959. UCSB expanded its academic program under his leadership. In July of 1962, Gould became president of the Educational Broadcasting System in New York with the flagship station, WNDT-TV, channel 13.
In 1964, Gould was appointed chancellor of the State University of New York (SUNY). During his administration, SUNY underwent its greatest physical and academic expansion and consolidation. Gould's vision for SUNY went beyond a desire to establish a traditional university system. He included in the university system new technologies such as television and non-traditional study opportunities such as those provided by the Empire State College teacher-mentor system. Under his tenure, the concept of granting academic credit for non-academic experience was initiated.
In 1970, Gould retired from SUNY, became Chancellor Emeritus and served briefly as a director at McKinsey and Company. From 1971 to 1974, he served as the chairman of the Carnegie Commission on Non-Traditional Study which attempted to modify and set new goals for education. During the 1970s Gould worked periodically with the Venezuelan Ministry of Education in developing that nation's university system. He accompanied former United States Vice President Nelson A. Rockefeller, a close personal friend, on his 1977 tour of Latin America. From 1976 to 1977, he served as interim chancellor for higher education for the State of Connecticut. He has also served as a trustee of the Teachers Insurance and Annuity Association and on the Commission for Post-Secondary Educational Planning in Florida.
Gould died on June 11, 1997.
Scope and Contents
The Samuel B. Gould Papers document's his long career in the field of higher education. This collection is divided into four series arranged chronologically: Biographical Material, Speeches, Reports and Published and Unpublished Works, and Administrative Files.
The Biographical Material series generally contains news and magazine clippings reporting events of Gould's life, particularly his tenure as chancellor at SUNY. There are also some articles on Gould's wife and two interviews with Gould as well as pictures of Laura Gould's paintings. This series also contains personal and professional photographs and Gould's naval orders and assignments.
By far the most extensive element in the papers are Gould's speeches, which cover the period of his presidency at Antioch College through his retirement. Speeches were Gould's primary means of communicating his ideas and views. Many of the speeches are repeated, with modifications for the audience and event, a process that was assisted by a 1969 condensed version of his ideas on education compiled by his SUNY staff. His speeches discuss trends in educational techniques and philosophies, including developments in non-traditional approaches and the use of electronic media. These also document the development of his programs for expansion at Antioch College, the University of California at Santa Barbara, the Educational Broadcasting System, the State University of New York, and the Carnegie Commission on Non-Traditional Study. The researcher should note that each speech's title is proceeded by the institution in which Gould served at the time of the speech.
Samuel Gould's reports, published articles and books are generally extensions of ideas previously expressed in his speeches and lectures. The third series contains many published and unpublished works of Gould's, including his unpublished autobiography A Maverick in the Establishment. Some folders contain correspondence about publishing articles and book reviews, as well as requests for re-print.
The last series, Administrative Files, contains materials from Gould's administrative roles, such as memorandums and press releases.
Separated Materials
The archivist transferred 22 monographs: The Asian Mystique written by Carlos P. Romulo, College and University: The Journal of the American Association of Collegiate Registrars and Admissions Officers edited by William C. Smyser, Curriculum Planning to Meet Tomorrow's Needs, Report of Twenty-Fourth Education Conference edited by Arthur E. Traxler, Diversity by Design: Commission on Non-Traditional Study written by Samuel B. Gould, Explorations in Non-Traditional Study edited by Samuel B. Gould and K. Patricia Cross, Forty-Fifth Anniversary Conference of the National Association of Student Personnel Administrators, The Graduate Journal, Vol. VIII, No. 2, edited by Audrey Nelson Slate, Higher Education: Myths, Realities and Possibilities edited by Winfred L. Godwin and Peter B. Mann, In Search of Leaders edited by G. Kerry Smith, In These Times: A Look at Graduate Education with Proposals for the Future edited by W. Gordon Whaley, Knowledge is Not Enough: Views on Higher Education written by Samuel B. Gould, Learning Today, Vol. 13 No. 2, edited by Howard Clayton, Library Journal edited by Eric Moon, Memoria: I Congreso Mundial de Educaion Continua para Ingenieros, National Association of Schools of Music Meeting Proceedings 1977 published by National Association of Schools of Music, Proceedings of the 1971 Invitational Conference on Testing Problems published by Educational Testing Service, Report of the San Diego TEPS Conference published by National Commission on Teacher Education and Professional Standards, Student Use of Libraries published by the American Library Association, two copies of Today’s Academic Condition written by Samuel B. Gould, Training the Local Announcer written by Samuel B. Gould and S. A. Diamond, The Will to Think: A Treasury of Ideas and Ideals from the pages of Think edited by Robert Cousins to the book division of Special Collections. These were cataloged and included in the University Library Catalog.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized into the following series:
Series 1 - Biographical Material, 1933-1997, Undated
Series 2 - Speeches, 1954-1985, Undated
Series 3 - Reports and Published and Unpublished Works, 1936-1980, Undated
Series 4 - Administrative, 1964-1989, Undated
All series are arranged chronologically.
State University of New York SUNY, Central Administration; Education; Education, Higher--California; Universities and colleges--Administration; Education, Higher--New York (State); Education, Higher--Ohio; Speeches (documents); Articles; Monographs; Photographs; Gould, Samuel B; State University of New York; University of California, Santa Barbara; Antioch College; Educational Broadcasting Corporation; Institute for Educational Development; Commission on Non-Traditional Studies
- Biographical Material, 1933-1997; Undated; 1; 0.92 cubic ft.
  Arrangement
  Arranged chronologically.
  Scope and Contents
  The series contains newspaper and magazine articles and interviews relating to Gould's SUNY chancellorship, his involvement on the Commission on Non-Traditional Study, and a 1980 interview covering his educational career. Also included is a folder on the activities of his wife, Laura, and their son's marriage. It also contains a large amount of photographs, both personal and professional in nature. Gould's naval orders and assignments can also be found in this series.
  - Personal Photographs, 1933-1935; 1955; 1967; Undated (Box 1 (1-Biographical Material), Folder 1-2)
  - Personal and Professional Photographs, 1938-1941; 1952-1990; Undated (Box 1 (1-Biographical Material), Folder 3)
  - United States Navy Orders and Assignments, 1942-1950 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Material), Folder 4)
  - Photographs and Portraits of Gould, 1947; 1959-1969; Undated (Box 1 (1-Biographical Material), Folder 5)
  - Photographs sent to Gould by Dr. Kay Glasser, 1947; 1959-1971; Undated (Box 1 (1-Biographical Material), Folder 6-7)
  - Event Hosted for Gould at the Horseshoe Room, 1957 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Material), Folder 8)
  - Various clippings on Mrs. Gould and Family, Plus the Program for "A Celebration of Philanthropy", 1958-1981 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Material), Folder 9)
  - USCB Inauguration Album with Newspaper Clippings and Congratulatory Letters, 1959 (Oversized 3)
  - Professional Photographs, 1959; 1962-1967; Undated (Box 1 (1-Biographical Material), Folder 10)
  - Gould's Appearance on "Newsmakers", 1962 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Material), Folder 11)
  - "State University Chief's Top Goal: Academic Excellence,"Knickerbocker News, 1964 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Material), Folder 12)
  - Welding 58 Schools into One Big University,"BusinessWeek, 1964 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Material), Folder 13)
  - Newsclippings about Gould's Presidential Inauguration, 1964-1965 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Material), Folder 14)
  - Presidential Inauguration Program, Articles, and Correspondence, 1964-1965 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Material), Folder 15)
  - Articles and Biographies on Gould, 1964-1975; 1997; Undated (Box 1 (1-Biographical Material), Folder 16)
  - Inauguration Photographs, Tickets, and Programs sent by LIFE Magazine, ca. 1965 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Material), Folder 17)
  - Album of SUNY Chancellor Inauguration Photographs and Congratulatory Letters, 1965 (Oversized 2)
  - Honorary Medals from UCSB, Colgate University, Channel Thirteen, SUNY Chancellor Inauguration, and New College of Florida, 1965; 1969; 1983; Undated (Oversized 4)
  - Photographs from Laura Gould's Art Exhibit, 1966 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Material), Folder 18)
  - "New York's Late Blooming State University,"Harper's Magazine, 1966 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Material), Folder 19)
  - "Profiles-A Certain Attitude Towards Change,"New York Magazine, 1967 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Material), Folder 20)
  - "The Giant That Nobody Knows,"TIME Magazine, 1968 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Material), Folder 21)
  - "Two Giants That Nobody Knows,"Albany Times Union, 1968 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Material), Folder 22)
  - Plaque in Recognition of Gould's Service as Chancellor of the State University of New York, ca. 1970 (Oversized 4)
  - Honorary Degree Ceremony at University of Pittsburgh, 1970; Undated (Box 1 (1-Biographical Material), Folder 23)
  - U.S. News and World Report Interview, 1970 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Material), Folder 24)
  - "Gould Questions College Process," Review of Today's Academic Condition, 1970 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Material), Folder 25)
  - Chancellor Emeritus and Honorary Degree Nomination, 1970; 1984 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Material), Folder 26)
  - "Who's Who in Higher Education,"Change Magazine, 1975 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Material), Folder 27)
  - "Commencement Speaker: Innovator Samuel Gould," Program for Aquines College Commencement, ca. 1976 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Material), Folder 28)
  - Personal Correspondence, 1979-1983 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Material), Folder 29)
  - Oral History Interview for TIAA-CREF, 1980 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Material), Folder 30)
  - Cover Pages for Books Written by Gould, 1980; Undated (Box 1 (1-Biographical Material), Folder 31)
  - Honorary Doctorate Degree from the State University of New York, 1985 (Oversized 1)
  - Correspondence with Martin Fausold about SUNY Oral History Project, 1987-1992; Undated (Box 1 (1-Biographical Material), Folder 32)
  - Photographs Sent by NYU and a Sketch of Gould, Undated (Box 1 (1-Biographical Material), Folder 33)
  - Photograph with President Lyndon B. Johnson, Undated (Box 1 (1-Biographical Material), Folder 34)
  - Photographs of Laura Gould's Paintings, Undated (Box 1 (1-Biographical Material), Folder 35)
  - Photographs from Various Vacations, Undated (Box 1 (1-Biographical Material), Folder 36)
  - Oversized Photographs of Samuel Gould, Laura Gould, and Unidentified Individuals, Undated (Oversized 4)
- Speeches, 1954-1985; Undated; 2; 2.50 cubic ft.
  Contains speeches of Samuel Gould as president of Antioch College (1954-59), chancellor of University of California at Santa Barbara (1959-62), president of the Educational Broadcasting System (1962-64), chancellor of SUNY (1964-70), chancellor emeritus (1970), director at McKinsey and Company (1971), chairman of Commission on Non-Traditional Study (1971-72), president of Institute of Educational Development/Research and a number of addresses he gave as a private citizen. The main topics of the speeches were educational reform and university life. The speeches from Gould's tenure as president of Antioch College are bound together in one volume.
  - Antioch Speeches, 1954-1959 (Oversized 1)
  - Guide to Antioch College Speeches, 1954-1959 (Box 1 (2-Speeches), Folder 37)
  - UCSB, "An Anchor or a Rudder," Assembly for New Students, 1959 September 15 (Box 1 (2-Speeches), Folder 38)
  - UCSB, "To Sing With the General Voice," Citizens Committee Inaugural Banquet Address, 1959 September 17 (Box 1 (2-Speeches), Folder 39)
  - UCSB, "The Level of Expectation," Inaugural Address, 1959 September 18 (Box 1 (2-Speeches), Folder 40)
  - UCSB, "Mental Health--A Dimension in Education," Mental Health Association Banquet, 1959 September 28 (Box 1 (2-Speeches), Folder 41)
  - UCSB, "Teacher Education--Substance and Spirit," Santa Barbara Public School Personnel, 1959 October 03 (Box 1 (2-Speeches), Folder 42)
  - UCSB, "The Noblest Mission," Beverly Hills Unified School District, 1959 October 14 (Box 1 (2-Speeches), Folder 43)
  - UCSB, "Man and Superwoman," Zonta International Annual Banquet, 1959 October 17 (Box 1 (2-Speeches), Folder 44)
  - UCSB, "College Education: A Threshold to Maturity," Pasadena College Assembly, 1959 November 05 (Box 1 (2-Speeches), Folder 45)
  - UCSB, "Education vs. Schooling," The University Explorer Radio Show, University of California Radio and Television Administration, Columbia Broadcasting System, 1959 November 08 (Box 1 (2-Speeches), Folder 46)
  - UCSB, "Daughters of a New Revolution," American Association of University Women Banquet, 1959 November 17 (Box 1 (2-Speeches), Folder 47)
  - UCSB, "Adult Education: An Ingredient of Responsibility," California Adult Education Administration, 1959 November 29 (Box 1 (2-Speeches), Folder 48)
  - UCSB, "The Impact of College on Student Attitudes and Values," Mt. San Antonio Junior College, 1959 December 07 (Box 1 (2-Speeches), Folder 49)
  - UCSB, "Mankind Is Our Business," Boy Scout Recognition Dinner, 1959 December 12 (Box 1 (2-Speeches), Folder 50)
  - UCSB, The Architectural Master Plan, ca. 1960 (Box 1 (2-Speeches), Folder 51)
  - UCSB, "Fifth Annual Robert Flaherty Film Seminar", ca. 1960 (Box 1 (2-Speeches), Folder 52)
  - UCSB, "Acceptance of the Gymnasium", ca. 1960 (Box 1 (2-Speeches), Folder 53)
  - UCSB, "The Student As Ambassador--Part I," American Field Service Regional Conference, 1960 January 03 (Box 1 (2-Speeches), Folder 54)
  - UCSB, "Mankind Is Our Business," Farm and Home Conference Banquet, 1960 January 29 (Box 1 (2-Speeches), Folder 55)
  - UCSB, "The Student As Ambassador--Part II," American Field Service Regional Conference, 1960 January 30 (Box 1 (2-Speeches), Folder 56)
  - UCSB, "The Teacher and the Curriculum," Institute Meeting for the Faculty of El Camino College, 1960 February 01 (Box 1 (2-Speeches), Folder 57)
  - UCSB, "The Splendor of Our Failures," Banquet, University Affiliates of U.C.L.A., 1960 February 15 (Box 1 (2-Speeches), Folder 58)
  - UCSB, "Faith and Contemporary Life," Religion in Life Banquet, 1960 February 28 (Box 1 (2-Speeches), Folder 59)
  - UCSB, "Mankind Is Our Business," California Industrial Education Association, 1960 March 12 (Box 1 (2-Speeches), Folder 60)
  - UCSB, "Daughters of a New Revolution," California Association of Women Deans Annual Banquet, 1960 March 19 (Box 1 (2-Speeches), Folder 61)
  - UCSB, "Mankind Is Our Business," Charter Day, San Francisco Medical Center, University of California, 1960 March 22 (Box 1 (2-Speeches), Folder 62)
  - UCSB, "Mankind Is Our Business," Pacific Palisades Civic League Banquet, 1960 March 28 (Box 1 (2-Speeches), Folder 63)
  - UCSB, Remarks--Charter Day Banquet, 1960 April 06 (Box 1 (2-Speeches), Folder 64)
  - UCSB, "The Promised Land," Charter Day Banquet, 1960 April 06 (Box 1 (2-Speeches), Folder 65)
  - UCSB, "Educational Values in Cooperative Education," A statement for Study of Cooperative Education, 1960 May 24 (Box 1 (2-Speeches), Folder 66)
  - UCSB, "A Goodly Outside," Commencement exercises, Upland College, 1960 May 28 (Box 1 (2-Speeches), Folder 67)
  - UCSB, "Report on Yugoslavia," American Association for the United Nations, 1960 June 01 (Box 1 (2-Speeches), Folder 68)
  - UCSB, "Turning the Hour Glass," Commencement Address, 1960 June 08 (Box 1 (2-Speeches), Folder 69)
  - UCSB, "The Exhilaration of Adversity," Commencement Exercises, Pomona College, 1960 June 12 (Box 1 (2-Speeches), Folder 70)
  - UCSB, "Thirty Minutes From Oblivion," San Bernardino College Commencement, 1960 June 17 (Box 1 (2-Speeches), Folder 71)
  - UCSB, "A Goodly Outside," Commencement Exercises, Monterey Peninsula College, 1960 June 18 (Box 1 (2-Speeches), Folder 72)
  - UCSB, "The Essence of Accreditation," National Commission on Teacher Education, 1960 June 22 (Box 1 (2-Speeches), Folder 73)
  - UCSB, "Are the Liberal Arts Always Liberal?," Music Teachers' Association of California, 1960 July 18 (Box 1 (2-Speeches), Folder 74)
  - UCSB, Gould Memorandum for Insertion in a Handbook on Intramural Sports, 1960 August 30 (Box 1 (2-Speeches), Folder 75)
  - UCSB, "Quality in Learning and Teaching," San Mateo School District Meeting, 1960 September 05 (Box 1 (2-Speeches), Folder 76)
  - UCSB, "Quality in Learning and Teaching," Alameda Teachers Institute, 1960 September 08 (Box 1 (2-Speeches), Folder 77)
  - UCSB, "The Maturing Student in a Maturing University," Opening Convocation, 1960 September 15 (Box 1 (2-Speeches), Folder 78)
  - UCSB, The Intangible Ingredients," Tea for Women Affiliates, University Religious Conference, 1960 October 21 (Box 1 (2-Speeches), Folder 79)
  - UCSB, "The True Measure of Growth," The Affiliates of the U.C.S.B., Organizational Dinner, 1960 October 24 (Box 1 (2-Speeches), Folder 80)
  - UCSB, "A University View of the Junior College," Luncheon, California Junior College Association, 1960 October 26 (Box 1 (2-Speeches), Folder 81)
  - UCSB, "The Dimensions of a Teacher," California Schoolmasters Club, 1960 November 22 (Box 1 (2-Speeches), Folder 82)
  - UCSB, "The Blessings of America," Goleta Community Service, 1960 November 24 (Box 1 (2-Speeches), Folder 83)
  - UCSB, "Mens' Goals and Values in Society," Biennial Conference, U.C. Agricultural Extension Service, 1961 January 17 (Box 1 (2-Speeches), Folder 84)
  - UCSB, "Changing Pattern of Student Personnel Work," Western Association of Deans of Students, 1961 January 27 (Box 1 (2-Speeches), Folder 85)
  - UCSB, "The Pursuit of Excellence--Appreciation of Excellence in Youth,", 1961 February 24 (Box 1 (2-Speeches), Folder 86)
  - UCSB, "A New Innocence of Perception," Religion in Life Banquet, 1961 March 05 (Box 1 (2-Speeches), Folder 87)
  - UCSB, "One Rung of the Ladder," Charter Day Convocation, 1961 March 21 (Box 1 (2-Speeches), Folder 88)
  - UCSB, Chapter Day Banquet, 1961 March 21 (Box 1 (2-Speeches), Folder 89)
  - UCSB, "The Values We Live By," Annual Conference, California Association of Public School Business Officials, 1961 April 10 (Box 1 (2-Speeches), Folder 90)
  - UCSB, "The Bed of Procrustes," Los Felis Hollywood Jewish Community Center, 1961 April 20 (Box 1 (2-Speeches), Folder 91)
  - UCSB, "The Maturing Student in a Maturing University," Honors Convocation, University of Colorado, 1961 April 24 (Box 1 (2-Speeches), Folder 92)
  - UCSB, "The Citizen and the Educational Frontier," California Congress of Parents and Teachers, 1961 May 03 (Box 1 (2-Speeches), Folder 93)
  - UCSB, "A University Administration View of University Extension," National University Extension Association, 1961 May 07 (Box 1 (2-Speeches), Folder 94)
  - UCSB, "The Undertow of Progress," Commencement, 1961 June 10 (Box 1 (2-Speeches), Folder 95)
  - UCSB, "The Exhilaration of Adversity," Commencement Exercises, Bakersfield College, 1961 June 10 (Box 1 (2-Speeches), Folder 96)
  - UCSB, "The Exhilaration of Adversity," Commencement Exercises, Orange County State College, 1961 June 11 (Box 1 (2-Speeches), Folder 97)
  - UCSB, "The Experimental Thrust in Higher Education," Princeton Conference on Work Study in Higher Education, 1961 June 28 (Box 1 (2-Speeches), Folder 98)
  - UCSB, "Life's Ennobling Dimensions," Commencement Exercises, Knapp College of Nursing, 1961 August 27 (Box 1 (2-Speeches), Folder 99)
  - UCSB, "The Student and His World," Opening Convocation, 1961 September 14 (Box 1 (2-Speeches), Folder 100)
  - UCSB, "Patriot of the World," Memorial Service for Dag Hammarskjold, 1961 September 25 (Box 1 (2-Speeches), Folder 101)
  - UCSB, "Two Worlds Out of Many," Chapel Service, Thatcher School, 1961 October 29 (Box 1 (2-Speeches), Folder 102)
  - UCSB, "Santa Barbara County's Diverse Economy," Salute to Santa Barbara County, 1961 November 08 (Box 1 (2-Speeches), Folder 103)
  - UCSB, "A New Window on the World," Thomas Alva Edison Foundation, 1962 February 02 (Box 1 (2-Speeches), Folder 104)
  - UCSB, "The Impact of Science Upon Education," Chancellor's Seminar, 1962 February 06 (Box 1 (2-Speeches), Folder 105)
  - UCSB, "To Travel Hopefully," Chancellor's Report, 1962 March 13 (Box 1 (2-Speeches), Folder 106)